A Guide to the Medical College of Virginia Dental Class of 1951 Newsletter
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Medical College of Virginia Dental Class of 1951 Newsletter 1952-2001
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
2001/Nov/10
.8 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Lewis T. Rogers and the reunion committee of the Dental Class of 1951 on the occasion of their 50th reunion. Material added to the collection in 2011 were donated by the School of Dentistry.
Biographical/Historical Information
Painless Publication was the class newsletter for the Medical College of Virginia's Dentistry Class of 1951. This class was unique in that it was the first class to graduate under Dean Harry Lyons and all of the members were World War II veterans.
Each class member, in alphabetical order, edited the yearly publication compiled from his classmate's letters. In 1993, the cycle renewed much to the amazement of the class members. Each class member was encouraged to write a short synopsis of the year before. These synopses include personal and professional accomplishments, photographs, newspaper clippings, retirements, and more recently obituaries of class members.
In 2011, the class celebrated its 60th anniversary. To mark the occasion the VCU School of Dentistry and Tompkins-McCaw Library honored the members of the class and the surviving spouses on April 16, 2011. The celebration was attended by the alumni and guests, current dental students, and the faculty and staff of the dental school and library. The day's events included an open house at the library, followed by a Military Salute to the DDS Class of 1951 and reception held in the Lyons and Perkinson buildings of the dental school. The culminating event was the unveiling of a commemorative plaque at the dental school honoring the Class of 1951's "service to the nation, support of the school, and inspiring class camaraderie." Class members were later sent a commemorative coin, designed by Sara Stires, DDS Class of 2011, and booklet about the event as mementos of the occasion.
Scope and Content
The newsletter is for and by the membership of the Medical College of Virginia's Dental Class of 1951. It contains personal information shared among class members including personal and professional accomplishments, membership roster, photographs, and observations of the dental field.
Additional materials were added to the collection in 2011 relating to the 60th class reunion celebration. These materials include thank you letters from the alumni and family members who attended the reunion; copies of the Military Salute to the DDS Class of 1951, a booklet detailing the event including speakers' remarks, photographs, and a large foldout image of the commemorative plaque honoring the class; and a commemorative coin commissioned to mark the occasion. Also of note is a University College of Medicine (UCM) pin sent by Lucille Lewis Armstrong, wife of 1951 class member Dr. Thomas W. Armstrong, Jr. The pin belonged to her father, Maryan Buford Lewis, DDS, a 1905 UCM graduate.
Arrangement
The collection follows the original arrangement with issues listed in chronological order.
Contents List
- Painless Publication 1952 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Painless Publication 1953 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Painless Publication 1954-1956 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Painless Publication 1958-1961 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Painless Publication 1962-1969 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Painless Publication 1970-1977 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Painless Publication 1978-1983 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Painless Publication 1984-1988 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Painless Publication 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Painless Publication 1991-1993 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Painless Publication 1994-2011, Spiral bound volumes for each year (Box 2)
- Thank you letters, 2011 (Box-folder 3:1)
  This folder also contains the UCM pin attached to the note from Lucille Lewis Armstrong.
- Military Salute to the DDS Class of 1951 booklet, 16 April 2011 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Photographs and misc., 2011 (Box-folder 3:3)
  Photographs of the reunion event on CD, a list of address of class members, and a complete list of Painless Publications issues and editors.
- Commemorative coin (Box 3)